Susannah Armstrong Coleman Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Susannah Armstrong Coleman Collection 1912-1953 (bulk 1930-1949)
ML31.C65
Coleman, Susannah Armstrong
circa 169 items 3 containers 1 linear foot
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Susannah Armstrong Coleman (1897-1985) was an American pianist, composer and teacher. The Susannah Armstrong Coleman Collection consists of music manuscripts, organizational publications, correspondence, programs, photographs, biographical notes, clippings, and miscellaneous items.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Coleman, Susannah Armstrong--Archives.; Coleman, Susannah Armstrong--Correspondence.; Coleman, Susannah Armstrong.; Coleman, Susannah Armstrong.; Oldberg, Arne, 1874-1962.
Organizations
Mu Phi Epsilon.; Northwestern University (Evanston, Ill.). School of Music.; Pi Kappa Lambda.
Subjects
Women composers--United States.; Women pianists--United States.
Form/Genre
Programs (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Estate of Susannah Armstrong Coleman, circa 1987.
Access and Restrictions
The Susannah Armstrong Coleman Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Susannah Armstrong Coleman (1897-1985) was an American pianist, composer, and teacher. Born in Chicago, Coleman began her musical studies locally with Hilda Brown before earning a bachelor's degree at the Northwestern University School of Music in 1919. There she studied piano with Victor Garwood, Josef Lhevinne, and Arne Oldberg, the latter with whom she also studied composition. She continued her piano studies abroad with Artur Schnabel from 1924-1925. Between 1930 and 1946, Coleman composed extensively while in summer residence on fellowship at the MacDowell Colony in Peterboro, New Hampshire. She moved to New York in 1934 and married former Colony member Laurence Vail Coleman four years later. The couple spent the remainder of their lives in the Washington, D.C. and Charlottesville, Virginia, areas while also travelling extensively throughout Europe and the Carribean. Over the course of her lifetime, Susannah Coleman won prizes for numerous compositions, including awards from Mu Phi Epsilon for her Blue Symphony and Mother Goose Suite.
Date Event
1897 March 11 Born Susannah Winifred Armstrong, Chicago, Illinois
1919 Earns Bachelor of Music, Northwestern University School of Music
1930 Awarded fellowship to study composition at the MacDowell Colony, Peterboro, New Hampshire
1939 Feb. 9 Marries Laurence Vail Coleman
1985 July Dies in Arlington, Virginia
Scope and Content Note
The Susannah Armstrong Coleman Collection spans the period 1912-1953; the bulk of the materials date from 1930-1949. The collection includes music manuscripts, organizational publications, correspondence, programs, photographs, biographical notes, clippings, and miscellaneous items. Correspondence principally consists of greeting cards from Mrs. Coleman's friends and acquaintances. The clippings focus on collegiate programs and the activities of her instructors at the Northwestern University School of Music. Pamphlets and publications of Mu Phi Epsilon and Pi Kappa Lambda portray Coleman as an invested member who actively contributed to organizational events.
Arrangement of the Susannah Armstrong Coleman Collection
The Susannah Armstrong Coleman Collection is organized into nine series:
Music
Publications
Correspondence
Programs
Photographs
Certificates and Academic Papers
Biographical Notes
Clippings
Miscellaneous
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006577448
Container List
- Music (Box 1-2)
  - The bagpipe man (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Barter (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Blue symphony (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Chimes (variations) (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Debate: for piano (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Debate: for two pianos (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Dusk (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Four compositions: Slumber song; Hunting song; Bells; Chinese dance (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Introit and differencia (Box-folder 1/9)
  - The King of China's daughter (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Men and wheat (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Missal theme (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Mother Goose suite (Box-folder 1/13)
  - The noise of waters (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Oh, where have you been Billy Boy? (Box-folder 2/1)
  - The oxen (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Pastoral suite (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Prelude, G sharp minor (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Promenade (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Pyrenees legend (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Rock-a-bye baby (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Quietly gone (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Sea shell (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Seven suite for piano (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Trio-andante con moto (Box-folder 2/11)
  - When that I was and a little tiny boy (Box-folder 2/12)
- Publications (Box 3)
  - Mu Phi Epsilon, June 23-26, 1948 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Pi Kappa Lambda, 1918-1937 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - The Triangle, 1947-1950 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - The Washington Season, Winter 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - YWCA (Young Women's Christian Association), 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3/4)
- Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Brown, Ray B. (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Clutcher, Ruth Row (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Garwood, Victor (Box-folder 3/5)
  - King, Bertha (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Klein, Dr. Charlotte (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Lutkin Quintette (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Lutkin, Lelah and Peter (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Oldberg, Arne (Box-folder 3/5)
- Programs (Box 3)
  - Programs, 1912-1926 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Recital by pupils of Miss Hilda B. Brown, The Woman's Library Club, Glencoe, Illinois, June 15, 1912 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Northwestern University School of Music, Evanston, Illinois, Thirty-ninth students' recital, Music Hall, Orrington Avenue and University Place, May 17, 1917 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Northwestern University School of Music, Evanston, Illinois, Forty-fourth students recital, Music Hall, Orrington Avenue and University Place, May 23, 1918 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Northwestern University School of Music Evanston, Illinois, Sixth alumni recital, Music Hall, Orrington Avenue and University Place, May 1, 1919 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Northwestern University School of Music, Evanston, Illinois, Third alumni recital, December 6, 1920 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Glencoe Men's Club entertainments recital, February 4, 1921 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Glencoe Men's Club entertainments recital by Mr. Attilio Baggiore, tenor, assisted by Miss Susannah Armstrong, pianist, Miss Bertha Hagen, accompanist, February 4, 1921 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Northwestern University School of Music Evanston, Illinois, Twenty-fifth student recital, March 25, 1924 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Enlightenment, a pageant commemorating the quarto-centennial anniversary of the birth of New Trier Township High School, June 14 and 15, 1926 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Enlightenment, Twenty-Fifth Anniversary, 1926 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Programs, 1927-1953 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Northwestern University School of Music, Thirty-second student recital, June 9, 1927 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Northwestern University School of Music, First alumni recital, December 8, 1927 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Dedication exercises, Central School auditorium, Glencoe, Illinois, May 31, 1929 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - A spring festival, Saturday evening, April 27, 1935 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Recital by new members of the faculty of Gardner School, Friday evening, October 25, 1935 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - The National Association for American Composers and Conductors, Steinway Concert Hall, March 16, 1937 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Elizabeth Layman Anning, pianist, Katherine Hamilton, violinist, Susannah Armstrong at the piano, November 9, 1937 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Friday Morning Music Club, Fifty-fifth season, Friday, February 28, 1941 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Friday Morning Music Club, Fifty-sixth season, Friday, February 27, 1942 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Friday Morning Music Club, Fifty-seventh season, February 12, 1943 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Friday Morning Music Club, Fifty-eighth season, December 10, 1943 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Arts Club of Washington, March, 2, 9, 12, 16, 23, 28, 29, 30, 1944 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Friday Morning Music Club, Fifty-eighth season, March 3, 1944 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Arts Club of Washington, February 1, 1945 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Friday Morning Music Club, Fifty-ninth season, April 6, 1945 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Friday Morning Music Club, March 15, 1946 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - The Arts Club of Washington, in a program for two pianos, April 11, 1946 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Friday Morning Music Club, February 14, 1947 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - 275th concert, National Gallery of Art, September 21, 1947 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Arts Club of Washington, May 13, 1948 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Arts Club of Washington, November 18, 1948 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Friday Morning Music Club, Friday, November 26, 1948 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - The Phillips Gallery, December 13, 1948 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - The Phillips Gallery, December 11, 1949 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Carnegie Recital Hall, February 13, 1951 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - The Arts Club, February 22, 1951 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - The Phillips Gallery, song recital, March 3, 1952 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - The Arts Club, January 22, 1953 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - The Friday Morning Music Club, Sixty-seventh season, February 6, 1953 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - First annual program of original compositions by the students of N.T.H.S. harmony classes, undated (Box-folder 3/7)
- Photographs (Box 3)
  - Trophy from an original composition contest of Mu Phi Epsilon (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Two portraits of Susannah Armstrong Coleman (Box-folder 3/8)
- Certificates and Academic Papers (Box 3)
  - Pi Kappa Lambda member certificate (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Mu Phi Epsilon demission certificate (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Examination papers, 3 p. (Box-folder 3/9)
- Biographical Notes (Box 3)
  - Notes prepared for various short biographies (Box-folder 3/10)
- Clippings (Box 3)
  - Clippings of Susannah Armstrong Coleman and her teachers (Box-folder 3/11)
- Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Biography and portrait of Arne Oldberg (Box-folder 3/12)